

1800 102 2558 | +91 9818882211











Total Experience: 18 Year(s) 0 Month(s)

Highest Degree: MBA/PGDM [Information Technology]

Associate Director seeking assignment in Software Development, Software Application Development, Project Management, Requirement Gathering, Solutions Architecture, Enterprise Architecture, Architecture Development, . Net framework , Crystal Reports, MS Visio



Current Designation: Associate Director of IT Architecture &

Strategy, Enterprise Architecture Manager

Current Company: Commercial International Bank (CIBeg.com)

Current Location: Cairo, Egypt

Pref. Location: United Arab Emirates (UAE), United Kingdom

(UK), United States (US)

Functional Area: IT Software - Application Programming

Maintenance

Role: Head/VP/GM-Technology(IT)/CTO

Industry: Banking/Financial Services/Broking

Marital Status: Married

 $Key Skills: Associate \ Director, Head \ NP/GM-Technology (IT)/CTO, Software \ Development, Software \ Application$ Development, Project Management, Requirement Gathering, Solutions Architecture, Enterprise Architecture, Architecture

Development, Net framework , Crystal Reports

Last Active: Jan-Mar 2021

Last Modified: Jan-Mar 2021

Jump to Section

Work Experience | Education | IT Skills |

Summary

More than 18 years of experience in Information and Communication Technology (ICT) field, out of which, more than 9 years in Senior Architect roles within banking industry, where held positions of Senior Integration Architect, Senior Enterprise Solutions Architect, and Enterprise Architecture Manager. During this journey, I've got exposed to different technology domains, different business areas, and different business transformation programs.

Work Experience

Commercial International Bank (CIBeg.com) as Associate Director of IT Architecture & Strategy, Enterprise Architecture Manager Sep 2012 to Till Date

CIB is consistently recognized on a global level as the 'Best Bank in Egypt', many awards have been received on numerous occasions by publications such as Global Finance, The Banker, Euro money and Emerging Markets. Global Finance has recognized CIB as the 'Best Bank in Egypt', for the last 10 years, The Banker has named it as 'Bank of the Year - Egypt', while Emerging Markets acknowledged it as 'Best Bank in North Africa'. That's through its superior management, high operating standards, and premier training programs. CIB continues to be the most profitable commercial bank in Egypt.

Associate Director of IT Architecture & Strategy, Enterprise Architecture Manager

- * Contribute in defining IT vision and mission, developing different strategies, evaluating and selecting best IT strategy to fulfill bank's strategic goals and objectives as they relate to ICTs.
- * Ensuring IT-Business alignment, building architectural transformation plans to bridge existing gaps in application, data and technology domains, steering its implementation and facilitating its delivery.
- * Participate in annual IT budgeting process, ensuring consistency with objectives' priorities and dependency. * Build and maintain a blueprint of the full landscape of IT services and solutions covering all domains,
- allowing for cross domain and deep what-if analysis, to support the CIO and the decision-making process.
- * Engage with business in the very early stage of requirements building, outlining the existing enterprise
- strengths, capabilities, and its transformational plans to ensure alignment and strategic goals achievement.
- * Prepare architectural artifacts, evaluate alternative solutions and document key decisions & its justification. * Define essential architecture principles and guidelines for different architecture domains as well as design features / framework standards for solution designers and developers to follow.
- * Liaise with technical and business stakeholders on different levels, considering their concerns and needs, selling the architecture strategic vision and getting the buy-in.
- * Assess, evaluate, and provide transformation roadmap and course of actions for legacy systems to cope with architectural vision, best practices, technology trends and definitely to server strategic bank directions.
- * Manage technical assessments, engage with vendors, lead RFP technical requirements, evaluate proposals, and review SOW and contracts.
- * Model enterprise solutions to be secure, agile and efficient, taking functional and non-functional requirements into consideration, capitalizing on existing investments and incorporating architecture

Important

· Using Free CV Search you have access to featured candidate profiles of Naukri. You can browse through the profiles and email the candidates of your choice directly using the email option provided. To prevent misuse of candidate information, contact details and attached resume of the candidates have been withheld

methodologies (SOA, EDA..)

- Adopting TOGAF framework and its architecture development method with required changes, and following BIAN (Banking Industry Architecture Network) standard to define business services / capabilities
- Enforcing architecture governance through architectural principles, internal/external process, templates, architecture review board, roles and responsibilities for accountability, OLAs, and performance measures.

* Sample of transformation programs / projects I've worked on during this period:

Consumer Transformation Program (Seibel CRM, Campaign Management and Marketing Automation, Complain Management, SRs, Customer 360, Account Opening, Loan Origination, Experian Decision Engine) Risk Transformation Programs (SAS Credit, Market, Operational and AML Risk Management Products) Corporate Internet banking (Msys corporate cash & trade portals MCP/MTP upgraded to FBCC and FBTI) Corporate Lending and CAM process (Moody's Platform using CreditLens for Rating, Spreading, Projections, Credit case management and Credit Approval Memo)

Consumer Banking (CR2 Internet Banking, Website and Analytics, Chatbot, IVR Revamp, Mobile Banking, mobile wallet, Omnichamnnel, Mastercard Loyalty (CIB Bonus), Credit Card Equal Payment Plan EPP, ...)

Ejada Systems as Senior Integration Architect (Message Broker migration project to zLinux) Apr 2003 to Aug 2012

EJADA is a leading IT services & solutions provider in Middle East & North Africa, EJADA is the 2nd largest services & solutions company in Saudi Arabia.

EJADA is number One in information system consulting, in application consulting and customization and also in custom application development based on IDC reports on the Saudi IT services market as of 2012.

Senior Integration Architect (Message Broker migration project to zLinux)
Dec 2011 - Aug 2012 Client: Riyad Bank Riyadh, Saudi Arabia
* This is an extra role in addition being part of Riyad Bank's Production Support team.

- * Preparing the As-Is and To-Be architecture along with the transformation plan for the whole migration project, covering technology, application, and data domains.
- Acting as a subject matter expert (SME), and products specialist, planning the whole migration across environments while ensuring nonfunctional requirements of each environment (i.e. ZERO down time).
- * Evaluating WMB/MQ on zLinux vs. existing WMB/MQ on AlX from financial standpoint. (TCO & ROI)
- * Supervising the migration of WMB code from v6.0 to v7.0.
- * Tools: IBM WebSphere Message Broker (WMB V6.0/7.0) (AIX / zLinux), IBM WebSphere MQ Series V7.0 (AIX/Win/zLinux)

Senior Integration Architect (Message Broker migration project to zLinux)

Dec 2011 - Aug 2012 Client: Riyad Bank Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- * This is an extra role in addition being part of Riyad Bank's Production Support team.
- * Preparing the As-Is and To-Be architecture along with the transformation plan for the whole migration project, covering technology, application, and data domains.
- Acting as a subject matter expert (SME), and products specialist, planning the whole migration across environments while ensuring nonfunctional requirements of each environment (i.e. ZERO down time).
- * Evaluating WMB/MQ on zLinux vs. existing WMB/MQ on AlX from financial standpoint. (TCO & ROI)
- * Supervising the migration of WMB code from v6.0 to v7.0.
- * Tools: IBMWebSphere Message Broker (WMB V6.0/7.0) (AIX/zLinux), IBMWebSphere MQ Series V7.0 (AIX/Win/zLinux)

WebSphere Message Broker Specialist (IBM Message Broker upgrade project)

April 2006 - April 2007 Client: Riyad Bank Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- * Upgrading & configuring all Riyad Bank's environments (Development, SIT, UAT, Production and Disaster Recovery), from MQSI v2.1 to WMB V6.0, and fine-tuned Prod. for required volume/capacity.
- * Covering all solution components (AIX Brokers, Windows Config. Managers, and Queue Managers).
- * Applying required code changes to comply with the new version and handled the source control conflicts.
- * Running the upgrade project in parallel to the current bank projects in different environments,
- * Ensuring ZERO down time cross environments.
- * Tools: MQ Series Integrator 2.1(MQSI) (AIX/Win), MQ 5.3(AIX/Win), WVB 6.0 (AIX/Win), DB2

Enterprise Application Integration Developer

July 2005 - Mar 2006 Client: Mobily Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- * Designed, developed and deployed deferent services for SIM, Number and Customer Management.
- * Participated in building testing scenarios and use cases.
- * Contributed in requirements gathering, analysis and specs writing as a part of business analysis team.
- * Tools: IBM WebSphere MQ Series 5.2, IBM WebSphere Message Broker 5.0.

Integration Developer

Dec 2004 - May 2005 Client: Riyad Bank Riyadh, Saudi Arabia

- * Asolo show where I've gathered the business requirements, designed and developed a three-tier, middleware adapter called e-Payment Gateway to automate Riyad Bank Payments to local and international vendors and also to automate paying Riyad Bank's due bills, all based on interfacing with middleware services.
- 2 level Approval and reporting facilities were also provided part of the gateway.
- * The adapter was running in PROD with a daily average of 35 Payment and 4.5 Million Saudi Riyal.
- Unilever Mashreq Co as Application Developer Jan 2003 to Apr 2003
- AlexWebTech as Database Administrator & Developer Sep 2001 to Jan 2003

^ Back to Top

Education

UG: B.Sc (Radiographer CT MRI TECH) from Faculty of engineering, Alexandria university in 2001 PG: MBA/PGDM (Information Technology) from Arab academy for science and technology in 2020

IT Skills

Skill Name	Version Last Used	Experience
IBMWebsphere Message Broker		
AIX/zLinux		
IBMWebSphere MQ Series V7.0		
Oracle PL/SQL, Rational ClearCase		
ClearQuest, BMC Remedy, BMC Patrol, Unix		

^ Back to Top

Languages Known

Language	Proficiency	Read	Write	Speak	
English		✓	✓	✓	
Arabic					

^ Back to Top

Affirmative Action

Work Authorization

Physically Challenged: No

Job Type: Permanent Employment Status: Full time

^ Back to Top

Careers - About Us - Clients - Terms & Conditions - FAQ's - Contact Us - Report a Problem - Site Map - Resources
Our Partners: Jeevansathi Matrimonials - ICIClcommunities.org - 99acres - Real Estate In India
All rights reserved © 2021 Info Edge India Ltd.

Careers - About Us - Clients - Terms & Conditions - FAQ's - Contact Us - Report a Problem - Site Map - Resources
Our Partners: Jeevansathi Matrimonials - ICIClcommunities.org - 99acres - Real Estate In India
All rights reserved © 2021 Info Edge India Ltd.